Register of the Rodolfo Echeverría Martínez Collection, 1911-1986
Hoover Institution Archives
Rodolfo Echeverría Martínez Collection,
1911-1986
87037
Echeverría Martínez, Rodolfo, collector.
34 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 phonotape (17 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, correspondence, minutes, conference proceedings, resolutions, speeches, pamphlets, discussion bulletins, newsletters, and printed matter, relating to activities of the Partido Comunista Mexicano from its formation in 1919 until its merger with other parties in 1981, including electoral, trade union, student and other activities, and activities both at the national level and within various states.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1987.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Communism--Mexico.; Communism.; Mexico.; Trade-unions--Mexico.; Mexico--Politics and government.; Trade-unions and communism.; Student movements--Mexico.; Education.; Phonotapes.; Partido Comunista Mexicano.
Historical Note
The Partido Comunista Mexicano (P.C.M.) was organized in September 1919 by Mexican socialists under the direction of Comintern representatives Manabendra Nath Roy and Michael Borodin. The political instability and radicalism of the final years of the Mexican Revolution, combined with a native tradition of anarcho-syndicalism and trade unionism, created a party with a large rural following, as well as strength among transport workers, miners, educators and intellectuals. The party probably reached maximum strength (approximately 30,000 members) during the Popular Front period, when it cooperated with the administration of President Lazaro Cardenas (1934-1940). By 1960, the membership was estimated at 3,000. In 1940, two important leaders, Hernan Laborde and Valentin Campa, expelled from the P.C.M. for "right opportunist deviation", formed the Partido Obrero-Campesino Mexicano (P.O.C.M.). In 1948, the Partido Popular Socialista (P.P.S.) was established by Vincente Lombardo Toledano. From its inception, the P.P.S. was more influential; its larger membership allowed its candidates to qualify for election registration, a goal which the P.C.M. was never able to achieve under the old electoral law.
After the 1968 protest movement and subsequent government repression, the P.C.M. abandoned attempts to cooperate with the the government party (Partido Revolucionario Institucional, P.R.I.) and organized to work for political rights and electoral reform. In the mid-1970's the P.C.M. formed electoral coalitions with other leftist groups; after 1978, electoral reform made it possible for the party to register legally and participate openly in elections. The political dominance of the P.R.I. disinclined the P.C.M. to concentrate on parliamentary activity, however. The greater focus was on creating a stronger mass-based party, leading to the unification of the P.C.M. with four other left-wing parties in 1981 to form the Partido Socialista Unificado de Mexico (P.S.U.M.).
Rodolfo Echeverría Martínez was a student activist in the late 1960's, and a member of the Executive Commission in the mid-1970's. Opposed to unification, he left the party in 1981. The material was assembled by Echeverria during and after his membership in the party, as well as from at least two other sources. Gabino R. Alcaraz was active in Michoacan in the 1920's and 1930's, initially as acting president of the Partido Socialista Michoacano (ca. 1925). By 1927, he was a member of the P.C.M. state Central Committee and responsible for agrarian affairs. His papers are organized as a separate series. Enrique Condes Lara was a member of the P.C.M. Central Committee in Puebla, and head of the electoral operation there; materials gathered by him are included in the section relating to the state of Puebla.
Sources:
Carr, Barry, Mexican Communism, 1968-1983: Eurocommunism in the Americas? San Diego: University of California Press, 1985
Schmitt, Karl M., Communism in Mexico: A Study in Political Frustration. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1965
Series Description
- PARTIDO COMUNISTA MEXICANO, CENTRAL COMMITTEE, 1921-1986. (Boxes 1-16)
  Reports, correspondence, agenda, minutes, flyers, miscellany, notes, meeting materials, speech transcripts, pamphlets, circulars, discussion bulletins, forms, lists, serial issues, budgets, interviews, newsletters, memoranda, charts, convocations, press releases, clippings, and resolutions. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- PARTIDO COMUNISTA MEXICANO, NATIONAL CONFERENCES, 1921-1982. (Boxes 17-21)
  Resolutions, reports, discussion bulletins, charts, circulars, pamphlets, statutes, press releases, outlines, notes, convocations, serial issues, speech transcripts, miscellany, and clippings. Arranged chronologically.
- PARTIDO COMUNISTA MEXICANO, REGIONAL COMMITTEES, 1935-1981. (Boxes 22-32)
  Reports, letters, instructions, miscellany, circulars, newsletters, minutes, resolutions, pamphlets, statutes, notes, lists, speech transcripts, press releases, clippings, flyers, sample ballots, forms, agenda, and discussion bulletins. Arranged alphabetically by state.
- GABINO R. ALCARAZ PAPERS, 1925-1963. (Box 33)
  Relates to P.C.M. activity in the State of Michoacan. Correspondence, forms, minutes, charts, circulars, miscellany, flyers, reports, newsletters, resolutions, and telegrams.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1919-1983. (Boxes 33-34)
  Relates primarily to other Mexican political organizations and parties. Newsletters, pamphlets, forms, circulars, flyers, pamphlets, instructions, bulletins, reports, leaflets, serial issues, and clippings. Arranged alphabetically by organizations.
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1911-1981. (Boxes 35-36)
  Newspapers, newsletters, circulars, declarations and election materials. Arranged to correspond with the previous series.
- PHONOTAPES, 1976. (Tape cabinet)
  One reel-to-reel phonotape
Container List
- PARTIDO COMUNISTA MEXICANO, CENTRAL COMMITTEE, 1921-1986
  - General
    - General
      - General, ca. 1928-1964. Song, miscellany, postcards, and a report relating to an information leak (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Circulars. Relating to the Federacion Juvenil Comunista, conferences, assassinations of members, and domestic and international political affairs, ca. 1929-1976 (Folder 2-5)
      - Correspondence. Letters by J. Encarnacion Perez, Manuel Terrazas, Valentin Campa, Agustin Montiel, and others, some of which were written from prison, 1934-1971 (Folder 6)
      - Meeting materials. Primarily material relating to plenary sessions
        - General. Letters, agenda, minutes, flyers, and miscellany, 1975-1979 (Folder 7)
        - 1934 Jan.-1935 Oct. Handwritten and mimeographed notes, a pamphlet and a printed article; primarily relates to the Frente Unico and international affairs, and plenary sessions of Jan. and Aug. 1934 (Folder 8)
        - 1937 June and Dec. Printed report and resolutions from plenary session, relating to anti-fascist unity (Folder 9)
        - 1941 Dec. Minutes of Buro Politico meeting, relating to national unity and international affairs, and internal organization and direction (Folder 10)
        - 1942 Nov. Report relating to party organization and development (Folder 11)
        - 1949 Oct. Reports, resolutions and a pamphlet by Dionisio Encino and J. Encarnacion Valdez entitled, Por la Paz, la Democracia y la Independencia Nacional (Folder 12)
        - 1956 Dec. Two plenary session reports relating to party organization and internal conflict, including one by J. Encarnacion Perez, and a pamphlet entitled, La Lucha Interna en el Partido Durante los Anos de 1939 a 1948: Caracteristicas Principales (Folder 13)
        - 1958 Jan.-May. Plenary session reports, notes, a pamphlet, and a report by Dionisio Encina primarily relating to internal conflict and activity (Folder 14)
        - 1959 July-Aug. Pamphlets relating to internal struggles, railroad strikes, political prisoners and the XXI Soviet Party Congress (Folder 15)
        - 1960 July. Discussion materials for a plenary session, including reports presented by Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo and Edelmiro Maldonado; includes material relating to Cuba (Folder 16)
        - 1961 July and Dec. Plenary session resolutions and a report by Edelmiro Maldonado relating to internal party conflict with the Federal District committee (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - 1962. Handwritten notes from unidentified meetings, relating to an economic campaign (Folder 2)
        - 1963 Feb. Mimeographed communication from J. Encarnacion Perez (from jail) to the plenary meeting, relating to international communism and specific situations in Cuba, Yugoslavia, China and Italy (Folder 3)
        - 1965-1972. Handwritten notes relating to meetings on student problems (Folder 4)
        - 1969 May-1973 May. Collection of handwritten notes covering numerous meetings during this period, primarily plenary and presidium sessions (Folder 5)
        - 1973 June and 1975 July. Memorandum and report to plenary session relating to party activities and goals (Folder 6)
        - 1976 April and Aug. Press release and reports, including two by Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo, relating to party growth and development and political reform (Folder 7)
        - 1977 Feb. Reports by Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo, list of agreements and miscellany (Folder 8)
        - 1977 March. Report by Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo entitled "El PCM Ante el Problema de la Unidad de Partidos Socialistas" (Folder 9)
        - 1977 (ca. May-June?). Report and resolutions relating to the party program and internal organization (Folder 10)
      - 1977 Sept.-1978 Feb. Primarily a collection of handwritten notes for multiple meetings (Executive Commission?), including a plenary session, 1977 Sept. (Folder 11)
      - 1978 Feb. Report by Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo (Folder 12)
      - 1978 Sept. Reports by Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo and Arturo Martinez Nateras (Folder 13)
      - 1979 May. Report (Folder 14)
      - 1979 August. Resolutions and reports relating to planned party activities, primarily electoral activity; includes Gilberto Enriquez Garcia, "Direcciones Principales del Trabajo de Construccion del Partido" and "Nuestra Presencia Electoral y las Nuevas Tareas en la Lucha por la Democracia" (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 1980 Feb. Discussion materials and a report by Gilberto Rincon Gallardo, "Las Comunistas en la Camara" (Folder 2)
      - 1980 May. Convocation, proposed agenda for the Nineteenth National Congress, a report entitled "La Propaganda del P.C." (Folder 3)
      - 1980 Dec. Printed pamphlet relating to party political activities (Folder 4)
      - 1981 April. Form letter, list of Central Committee members, and reports, primarily on organization (Folder 5)
      - 1981 May. Form letter, miscellany and a proposed resolution (Folder 6)
      - 1981 June. Form letter, reports, circular, miscellany, calendar of preliminary meetings for the Twentieth National Congress; includes materials relating to Poland (Folder 7)
      - 1981 July. Telegram, form letter, reports, and membership statistics (Folder 8)
      - 1981 Aug. 1-3. Leaflet and reports relating to political reform and the second party electoral convention (proposed for 1981 Sept.) (Folder 9)
      - 1981 Aug. 25-26. Financial report and charts, telegram, list of Central Committee members and a report on unification (Folder 10)
      - 1981 Sept. Circulars and a declaration of principles (Folder 11)
      - 1981 Oct. Report by Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo, "Nueva Etapa en la Lucha por el Partido de la Clase Obrera" and agreements relating to unification (Folder 12)
      - Membership materials. Pamphlet, identification cards, applications, letters, miscellany, circular, forms and flyers; includes letters from Rodolfo Echeverría Martínez, 1931-1981 (Folder 13)
      - Publications
        - General. Reports on party publishing concerns, statistics, letters, flyer, pamphlets, and a list, 1954-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        - Boletin de Informacion. Newsletters, 1963 Aug.-Nov. (Folder 2)
        - El Constructor. Newsletters, 1938 March-1944 April (Folder 3)
        - El Machete. Typed copies of articles, circulars, letter, serial issues, and meeting minutes, 1924-1964. SEE: OVERSIZE FILE for additional serial issues (Folder 4)
        - Machete. Serial issues, 1980 May-1981 July (Folder 5-6)
        - Nuestras Tareas. Bulletins, 1974 Jan.-1978 April (Folder 7)
        - Oposicion. Reports, budgets, circulars, flyers, schedules, lists and miscellany; includes materials relating to cultural festivals, 1975-1981. SEE: OVERSIZE FILE for newsletters (Box 5, Folder 1)
        - Socialismo. Serial issue, 1975 (Folder 2)
        - Teoria. Serial issues and a letter, 1947-1950 (Folder 3)
        - La Voz de Mexico. Copy of an article, circulars, financial materials, reports and a letter. SEE: OVERSIZE FILE for serial issues, 1943-1966 (Folder 4)
      - Speech transcripts. Printed copy of a speech by Dionisio Encina, a speech and a newspaper interview with Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo, 1943-1981 (Folder 5)
      - Statutes. Report with proposals and a pamphlet, 1981 (Folder 6)
    - Commissions and committees
      - Comision de Educacion, Agitacion y Propaganda (later Comision de Educacion y Propaganda). Letters, notes, description of function, educational materials, flyer, action plan and pamphlets, 1938-ca. 1979 (Folder 7)
      - Comision de Inspeccion y Disciplina (later Comision Central de Control). Letters, meeting reports, memorandum, and interrogations relating primarily to disciplinary actions, 1939-1978 (Folder 8)
      - Comision Nacional de Finanzas. Letters, plans, miscellany, receipts, budgets, flyers, circulars, charts, reports, a convocation and pamphlets; includes material relating to a national conference on finances and fund-raising campaigns, 1931-1980 (Folder 9)
      - Comision Nacional Juvenil. Action plans, speeches, resolutions, program, bulletins, newsletters (Joven Camarada), letters; includes material relating to the XI Festival Mundial de la Juventud y los Estudiantes and the Federacion Mundial de la Juventud Democratica, 1940-1978. SEE ALSO: Educational issues and youth organizations/Students/Juventud Comunista (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
      - Comision Nacional Sindical. Circulars, reports and resolutions relating to specific work conditions and general trade union programs, 1932-1979 (Folder 3)
      - Comision Politica. Letters, circulars, resolution, press release, report by Dionisio Encina, declarations and a flyer, 1948-1963 (Folder 4)
  - Agrarian issues. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE
    - General. Circular, statement, outline, reports by J. Encarnacion Perez and others, a pamphlet relating to sugar cane workers, meeting report and letters; includes a declaration on indigenous peoples, ca. 1931-1975 (Folder 5)
    - Central Campesina Independiente. Statutes and flyer, 1964-1965 (Folder 6)
    - Confederacion Nacional Campesina. Pamphlet, 1944 (Folder 7)
    - Liga Nacional Campesina. Circulars, proposed statutes, and a newsletter (Boletin de Bandera Roja, ) ca. 1931-1934) (Folder 8)
  - Educational issues and youth organizations
    - General. Reports and pamphlets; includes materials relating to educational programs for party members and workers, 1935-1979. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE (Folder 9)
    - Students
      - General. Reports, resolutions, newsletters, convocations, delegate identification form, and pamphlets, including material relating to the Central Nacional de Estudiantes Democraticos (CNED), 1935-1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Juventud Comunista. Resolutions, reports, letter, circulars, newsletters and pamphlets; includes materials relating to the second and third national congresses, 1933-1979 (Folder 2)
    - Teachers and university workers
      - Frente Magisterial Nacional. Newsletter (Educador Socialista), 1978-1979 (Folder 3)
      - Movimiento Revolucionario del Magisterio (MRM). Flyers, pamphlets, reports, resolutions, discussion materials and a press release, 1959-1976 (Folder 4)
      - Sindicato Nacional de Trabajadores de la Educacion (SNTE). Resolutions, reports, declarations, pamphlets, flyer, letter and discussion materials for a national meeting, 1958-1981 (Folder 5)
  - Elections. SEE ALSO: REGIONAL COMMITTEES/Puebla (and other states) and OVERSIZE FILE
    - General. Flyers, pamphlets, reports, lists, discussion materials, action plans, notes and a circular, relating to registration, electoral reform and conventions, 1957-1981 (Folder 6)
    - 1964. Plans, flyers, membership forms, list, position statements, letters, report, newsletter, speeches by Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo and Valentin Campa, agenda, instructions, pamphlets and circulars; includes materials relating to the Frente Electoral del Pueblo, 1963-1965 (Folder 7)
    - 1976. Plans, flyers, pamphlets and circulars relating to the presidential campaign of Valentin Campa, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1979. Instructions, reports, convocation, plans, forms, and pamphlets; includes material relating to the Coalicion de la Izquierda, 1978-1979 (Folder 2)
    - 1980. Report and flyer (Folder 3)
  - Electrical workers. Newsletter, circular, letter, statutes and a flyer, 1949-1972 (Folder 4)
  - Health workers. Reports and an agenda, 1965-1977 (Folder 5)
  - History of the party. Outlines, reports, and chronologies, including a report by Enrique Condes Lara entitled "Los Ultimos Anos del Partido Comunista Mexicano", ca. 1956-1985 (Folder 6-7)
  - Internal organization, development and conflict
    - General
      - General. Pamphlets, outlines, letters, newletter, plans, reports, instructions and statutes, 1944-1980. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
      - Leon Garza, Maximo de. "A Proposito de Algunas Concepciones del Grupo 'Espartaco'", 1966 (Folder 4)
      - Martinez Verdugo, Arnoldo. "Problemas Actuales del Desarollo del Partido," 1970 (Folder 5)
      - MacGregor Campuzano, Javier. "Crisis en una Organizacion Partidaria: El Partido Comunista Mexicano en la Decada de los Cuarenta," 1986 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Political programs and goals
      - Pamphlets, 1959-1981 (Folder 2)
      - Reports. Includes drafts and printed copies of Declaracion Programatica del Partido
        - ca. 1932-1979 (Folder 3-5)
        - 1980 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Trotskyism. Printed speech transcript by Hernan Laborde, a report by Jose Revueltas, and a pamphlet by Miguel Angel Velasco entitled La Lucha Contra el Trotskismo en los Anos 30, ca. 1938-1980 (Folder 2)
    - Unification. Flyers, declarations, press release, meeting minutes, and reports, 1977-1981. SEE ALSO: Twentieth Party Congress (Folder 3)
  - International communism and international affairs
    - General. Newsletters, pamphlets, reports, flyer, trip reports, letter, speech transcript and a resolution, 1921-1979 (Folder 4-6)
    - Afghanistan. Pamphlet, meeting agenda, reports and printed articles, 1980 (Folder 7)
    - Cuba. Pamphlets, newsletters, instructions, circulars, declarations and flyers, ca. 1926-1976 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Latin America
      - General. Pamphlets, declarations, reports, flyers and Central American newsletters, 1942-1984 (Folder 2)
      - Conferencia Latinoamericana por la Soberania Nacional, la Emancipacion Economica y la Paz. Flyers, pamphlets, speech transcript by Lazaro Cardenas, circulars, and declarations, 1961. SEE: OVERSIZE FILE for newsletters (Folder 3)
    - Soviet Union. Declarations, serial issue and reports, including U.R.S.S. Anuario para 1927, Rafael Ramos Pedrueza, La Estrella Roja: Doce Anos de Vida Sovietica, General Alberto Zuno Hernandez, El Ejercito y el Pueblo Sovieticos Vistos por un General Mexicano, and Hernan Laborde, La Biologica en la U.R.S.S.: Revolucion en la Genetica, 1927-1966 (Folder 4)
    - Trade union movement and syndicalism
      - General. Serial issue and pamphlets; includes material relating to the Fifth and Eighth World Syndical Congresses, 1961-1977 (Folder 5)
      - Boletin de la Internacional Sindical Roja, Secretariado Internacional de la Confederacion General del Trabajo Unitaria de Francia (C.G.T.U.)
        - 1928-1929 June (Folder 6-7)
        - 1929 July-1931 Dec. (Box 13, Folder 1-3)
      - Boletin Sindical, Consejo Central de los Sindicatos de la U.R.S.S., Comision de Relaciones Exteriores, 1929 Jan.-July (Folder 4)
    - United States. Convocation for the sixteenth convention of the Communist Party, U.S.A., a press release and reports on migrant workers and other subjects, ca. 1929-1979 (Folder 5)
    - World War II and the Popular Front. Pamphlets by Dionisio Encina and others, transcription of a speech by Josef Stalin, a speech by Dionisio Encina, a newsletter, miscellany, pamphlets, instructions, discussion report, miscellany, and a manifesto by the Communist Party of the U.S.A., 1931-1942. SEE ALSO: NATIONAL CONFERENCES/1940 Extraordinary Congress (Folder 6)
  - Mexican economics. Press release, pamphlets, outline, declarations and reports, 1945-1979. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE (Folder 7)
  - Mexican politics and government. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE
    - General. Circulars, pamphlets, press releases and reports, and an interview between the P.C.M. and President Jose Lopez Portillo; includes presidential statements and commentaries, and an open letter to Emilio Portes Gil, 1935-1978 (Folder 8-9)
    - Political prisoners and government repression. Circulars, pamphlets, meeting materials, lists, letters (including some from imprisoned leaders), flyers, declarations, press releases, resolutions, newsletter and pamphlets. Includes material relating to the Comite por la Libertad de los Presos Politicos y Defensa de las Garantias Constitucionales, and the arrest of David A. Siqueiros, including an inscribed copy of La Tracala: Mi Replica a un Gobierno Fiscal-Juez, 1959-1981 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Political reform. Reports, clipping and press releases, 1976-1980 (Folder 2)
  - Miners and metallurgical workers. Pamphlet, letter, proposal, report, discussion materials, and newsletter, 1928-1981 (Folder 3)
  - Petroleum workers. Reports, leaflet and material for a national meeting, ca. 1946-1977 (Folder 4)
  - Railway workers. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE
    - General. Pamphlets, newsletter, reports by Hernan Laborde and others, circulars, flyers, speech transcript and letters (Valentin Campa and Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo); includes materials relating to the Oposicion Sindical Revolucionaria Ferrocarrilera (OSRF), the Consejo Nacional Ferrocarrilero and the Sindicato de Trabajadores Ferrocarrileros, 1936-1980 (Folder 5)
    - 1959 strike. Flyers, pamphlets, newsletters, resolutions, reports by Jose Revueltas and others, and a booklet by Elias Barrios entitled, El Escuadron de Hierro, 1958-1959 (Folder 6)
  - Religion. Pamphlet, flyer, song and report, ca. 1928-1977 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Trade union movement and syndicalism. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE
    - General